Society for Canadian Women in Science and Technology fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Society for Canadian Women in Science and Technology fonds
1981 - 2005
F-39
Q70219248
3.13 m of textual records 403 photographs 22 sound recordings 2 artifacts 1 multi-media record
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: Photographs are located in series F-39-7 (390 photos), and in the following files: F-39-5-3-0-28 (5 photos), F-39-5-4-0-8 (6 photos), and F-39-5-5-0-3 (2 photos). Artefacts (2 buttons) are located in file F-39-6-0-0-9. Fonds also includes 29 audio cassettes (originals) and 1 CD (see item lists).
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of British Columbia through the Archives Association of British Columbia's Community Archives Assistance Program (March 2001); SFU's Faculty of Applied Sciences (March 2000); and the Society of Canadian Women in Science And Technology (March 2000). Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of these records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada's National Archival Development Program (2008).
Society for Canadian Women in Science and Technology
The Society of Canadian Women in Science and Technology (SCWIST) was founded in Vancouver BC in 1981 by six women: Mary Vickers, Hilda Ching, Abby Schwarz, Mary Jo Duncan, Diana Herbst, and Maggie Benston. SCWIST is a volunteer non-profit organization incorporated under the BC Societies Act; in 1984 it was registered as a charity under the federal Income Tax Act. It continues as an active organization.
SCWIST's mandate is to promote, support and empower women in the fields of science and technology. To this end, the Society works (i) to promote equal opportunities for women in scientific, technological and engineering careers; (ii) to improve social attitudes on the stereotyping of careers in science and educate the public about careers in science and technology; and (iii) to assist educators by providing current information on careers and career training, science and scientific policies. It realizes these goals through the organization of conferences and networking events, delivery of public educational outreach programs, production of resource material (videos, publications and handbooks), liaison with other organizations, and participation in granting, advocacy and advisory bodies.
From the six founders in 1981, membership in SCWIST grew rapidly to approximately 160 by 1984; subsequently, membership increased more slowly, reaching approximately 200 by 1993. The Annual General Meeting – held each spring and open to all members of the Society – votes on major decisions and elects the Executive Board of Directors. The Board is headed by the Society's president and meets regularly in Vancouver, while much of the on-going work of SCWIST is carried out by a number of standing and ad hoc committees appointed by the Board. Since 1992 SCWIST has maintained a permanent Resource Centre in Vancouver.
Major milestones in SCWIST history include the production of the Registry of Skilled Women, BC and Yukon (1983); the organization of the first National Conference on Women in Science and Technology (1983); the development of the following educational programs: Girls in Science (1984), Ms. Infinity (1990), and Project Tomorrow (1993); the establishment of the SCWIST scholarship (1986)--renamed the Maggie Benston Scholarship in 1991; the opening of a Resource Centre (1992); and the launching of the SCWIST web site (1997).
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the organization.
The fonds of the Society comprises records made and received in the course of administering the organization and carrying out its functions and programs. Geographically, SCWIST activities centre primarily on British Columbia. Activities documented include Annual General Meetings and monthly Executive Board meetings; administration of the Resource Centre; funding and financial management; liaison with other bodies; conferences and networking events; educational outreach programs; advisory work; advocacy and public relations. Records include constitution and by-laws; meeting agendas and minutes; correspondence; financial summaries and reports; presentations, reports and briefs; handbooks, manuals and publications; photographs; and audio recordings of Society conferences and workshops.
Series titles and arrangement are based on the most recent version of the Society's file classification plan, which was effective as of March 31, 2000. This plan is function-based and groups together records generated by activities falling under a similar function. Older records which may not originally have been organized according to any classification plan have been arranged according to these categories. The one exception concerns Series F-39-3, Liaison and cooperation records. This series and its title have been supplied by the archivist in order to group together files functionally related but which did not fall under any other classification. Because overlap among groupings can occur, please consult the entire file list in order to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject. Within files, documents generally follow chronological order.
When processing the third accession from SCWIST in 2008, the archivist created series F 39-7, Photographs, in order to group together snapshots that reflected activities described in a number of series.
Swenson, Sara; Matsui, Hiromi; Kellet, Rosalind; Issa, Maria; Gill, Jackie; LeCouteur, Penny; Berggren, Tasoula; Gonzales, Josefina; Herbst, Diana; Vickers, Mary; Dwyer, Betty; Ching, Hilda; Adair, Marian; Myers, Judy; Dawn McArthur; Stephanie Smith; Smith, Amanda; Ferenczi, Suzanne; Brief, Elana; Sound recordings; Moving images; Photographic materials; Textual records; Science and technology; Women
The records were donated to the Archives by SCWIST in two accessions in November 1997 and July 2000 respectively. The Archives received a third accession from SCWIST in January 2008.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2008. Further accruals are expected. According to the Agreement to Transfer signed by SCWIST and the Archives, the Society will donate its inactive records to the Archives once every five years.
The bulk of the records were in the custody of SCWIST member Maria Issa, who transferred them to the Archives in November 1997. A second, smaller accession of records from the Resource Centre was donated to the Archives in July 2000.
For other material relating to women in science, technology and trades, consult the inventories to the Kate Braid fonds (F 10), the Vancouver Women in Trades fonds (F 7), and the Women's Labour History Collection (F 67).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- Administrative records, 1991 - 1993; F-39-1; Analog originals: 5 cm of textual records 2 sound recordings (4 audiocassettes) Digitized materials: Preservation copies - 6 wav files (6.78 GB) Access copies - 6 mp3 files (297 MB)
  published
  Series comprises records relating to the establishment and operation of the SCWIST Resource Centre, which carries out many of the Society's administrative duties. The Resource Centre was opened in 1992 in offices at the Harbour Centre campus of Simon Fraser University, Vancouver. In 1996 it relocated to the downtown Vancouver YWCA building. The Centre is staffed by a paid Coordinator. Activities documented in this series include the establishment of the Resource Centre, its official opening in 1992, and staffing. Records consist of correspondence; grant applications and supporting documentation; reports; and invitations, guest book and audio recordings of the official opening.
  Analog originals were digitized by the Archives in October 2018. Digital copies are available in mp3 (access format) and wav (preservation format) for all sound recordings in this series. Please contact the reference archivist to request copies.
  For correspondence received and sent by the Resource Centre Coordinator, see series F-39-3, Liaison and cooperation records.
  - Resource Centre coordinator position, 1991 - 1992; F-39-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
    Textual records
    Restricted in whole
  - Resource Centre - grants and applications, 1991 - 1993; F-39-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
    Pending review
  - Resource Centre - grants and applications, 1992; F-39-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Resource Centre official opening, 1992; F-39-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
    - SCWIST Open House ceremonies, 1992; F-39-1-0-0-4-1 (Audio cassette OBJ-3078, Audio cassette OBJ-3079)
      Sound recordings
      Open
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-39-item1, F-39-item2.
    - SCWIST Open House – Hilda Ching, 1992; F-39-1-0-0-4-2 (Audio cassette OBJ-3080, Audio cassette OBJ-3081)
      Ching, Hilda; Sound recordings
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-39-item3, F-39-item4.
  - Resource Centre official opening - guest book, 1992; F-39-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
- Financial records, 1982 - 1994; F-39-2; 8 cm of textual records
  Series comprises records relating to the Society's management of its financial resources. Activities documented include application for registered charity status, internal reviews and monitoring of accounts, and annual tax and information returns. Records consist of accounting policies; account summaries and financial reports; correspondence; registration application form and supporting documentation; and annual tax and information returns.
  Records relating to funding and budgets for individual projects and programs are typically included in the project file; see series F-39-5, Projects, programs and events files.
  Financial statements are also typically included with the supporting papers of the Annual General Meetings; see series F-39-4, sub-series 2, Annual General Meeting files.
  For records relating to requests for SCWIST funding and the administration of SCWIST scholarships, see series F-39-8, Public Relations files.
  - Accounts - policy, 1992 - 1993; F-39-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Account summaries, 1989 - 1990; F-39-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Account summaries, 1990 - 1991; F-39-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Account summaries, 1991 - 1992; F-39-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Account summaries, 1992 - 1993; F-39-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Account summaries, 1993 - 1994; F-39-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Societies Act - annual reports, 1983 - 1993; F-39-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Taxes - registered charity applications, 1982 - 1984; F-39-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
  - Taxes - Revenue Canada registered charity information returns, 1985 - 1993; F-39-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 39-1)
- Liaison and cooperation records, 1981 - 1997; F-39-3; 28 cm of textual records
  Series comprises records relating to the Society's interaction and work with outside individuals, groups, coalitions and government bodies. Activities documented include responding to requests for information, membership or resource material; correspondence carried out by the President and other SCWIST officers; presentations and advice to governments; and participation of SCWIST in two other bodies – the Partners in Science Awareness Committee (PISAC, a provincially funded granting agency) and the Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WETC). Records consist of correspondence, reports and briefs; and copies of PISAC and WETC meeting minutes, support papers, and publicity brochures.
  This series was created by the archivist to group together material not readily fit into the Society's most recent (March 2000) file classification plan.
  For other records relating to the Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WETC), see the Vancouver Women in Trades fonds (F 9), series F-9-3, Liaison.
  - Commission of Inquiry on Equality in Employment, 1983; F-39-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence - logs, 1985 - 1993; F-39-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1981 - 1983; F-39-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 - 1992; F-39-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1984; F-39-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1985; F-39-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1986; F-39-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1986 - 1992; F-39-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1987 - 1988; F-39-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1988 - 1989; F-39-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1989 - 1990; F-39-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1990; F-39-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 - 1992; F-39-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1991 - 1992; F-39-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1992 - 1993; F-39-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1993; F-39-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1993 - 1994; F-39-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 39-2)
  - Correspondence, 1994; F-39-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Correspondence, 1994 - 1996; F-39-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Governments, 1992 - 1994; F-39-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Networking, 1991 - 1995; F-39-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Outside conferences, 1985 - 1989; F-39-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Outside conferences, 1992 - 1993; F-39-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Partners in Science Awareness committee - minutes, 1995 - 1996; F-39-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Partners in Science Awareness committee, 1995 - 1996; F-39-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Reports, briefs and presentations, 1985 - 1995; F-39-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Science World, 1990 - 1995; F-39-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WECT) - minutes, 1987 - 1991; F-39-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Women's Employment and Training Coalition (WECT) - correspondence, 1985 - 1991; F-39-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - Working group of Status of Women officials on Gender Equity in Education and Training, 1993; F-39-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 39-3)
  - MRC briefs incl. NSERC status, 1984; F-39-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - small 39-17)
  - Alberta conference - Women in Science, 1984; F-39-3-0-0-32 (Archival box - small 39-17)
  - Vancouver Foundation - correspondence, 1991 - 1997; F-39-3-0-0-33 (Archival box - small 39-17)
- Organization records, 1981 - 2005; F-39-4; 53 cm of textual records
  Series comprises records relating to the structure and governance of the Society as an organization. Activities documented include the establishment of the constitution and by-laws; reviews of SCWIST history; and Annual General Meetings and monthly Executive Board meetings. Records consist of constitution and by-laws; correspondence; reports; and meeting agendas, minutes and support papers.
  - Organizational structure and history files, 1981 - 1998; F-39-4-1; 5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records relating to the evolution of the Society, its mandate, structure and the duties of officers. Records consist of the SCWIST constitution and by-laws; correspondence; reports on job descriptions, roles and responsibilities; lists of Executive Board directors; and retrospective reviews of the Society's history.
    - Constitution and By-laws, 1984; F-39-4-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Executive Board officers, 1983 - 1996; F-39-4-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Organizational history and policy, 1982 - 1995; F-39-4-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Organizational history - general, 1981 - 1994; F-39-4-1-0-4 (Archival box - small 39-17)
    - Maggie Benston, 1993; F-39-4-1-0-5 (Archival box - small 39-17)
    - Grant - partners in organizational developent, 1998; F-39-4-1-0-6 (Archival box - small 39-17)
  - Annual General Meetings files, 1982 - 2005; F-39-4-2; 14 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records relating to the Society's Annual General Meeting (AGM) held each spring at the end of the fiscal year. The first AGM was held in 1982. AGMs are open to all members of the Society, and all members in good standing have full voting rights. At the AGM members receive reports from directors of the Executive Board and from committee chairs; elect new Executive Board directors for the coming year; approve nominations for honorary membership; determine membership fees; and vote on proposed motions, standing rules and amendments to the constitution or by-laws. Records consist of programs, agendas, minutes, reports, financial statements, audits, lists of nominations, proposals, motions and resolutions, publicity brochures and attendee lists.
    - Annual general meeting, 1982; F-39-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1983; F-39-4-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1984; F-39-4-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1985; F-39-4-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1986; F-39-4-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1987; F-39-4-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1988; F-39-4-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1989; F-39-4-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1990; F-39-4-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1991; F-39-4-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1992; F-39-4-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1993; F-39-4-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1994; F-39-4-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1995; F-39-4-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1996; F-39-4-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1997; F-39-4-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Annual general meeting, 1998; F-39-4-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Annual general meeting, 2001; F-39-4-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Annual general meeting, 2002; F-39-4-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Annual general meeting, 2003; F-39-4-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Annual general meeting, 2004; F-39-4-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Annual general meeting, 2005; F-39-4-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
  - Executive Board meeting files, 1981 - 1999; F-39-4-3; 34 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records relating to meetings of the Society's Executive Board of Directors. The Board consists of the president, two vice-presidents, treasurer, secretary, two directors at large, and the past president as a director ex officio. Directors are elected at the Annual General Meeting and serve one-year terms. The positions are all volunteer and directors are not remunerated, although they may be reimbursed for their expenses. According to the SCWIST constitution, Board meetings must be held at least four times per year, but typically meetings are held monthly. Board meetings are open to all members of the Society, but only directors may vote. The meeting hears reports from each director and committee, in addition to other Board business. Records consist of agendas, minutes, reports, financial statements, correspondence, proposals, and publicity brochures.
    - Minutes, 1981; F-39-4-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Minutes, 1982; F-39-4-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Minutes, 1983; F-39-4-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Minutes, 1984; F-39-4-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Minutes, 1985; F-39-4-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 39-4)
    - Minutes, 1986; F-39-4-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1987; F-39-4-3-0-7 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1988; F-39-4-3-0-8 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1989; F-39-4-3-0-9 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1990; F-39-4-3-0-10 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1991; F-39-4-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1992; F-39-4-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1993; F-39-4-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1994; F-39-4-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Minutes, 1995; F-39-4-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 39-5)
    - Attendance book, 1992 - 1993; F-39-4-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Minutes, 1996; F-39-4-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Minutes, 1997; F-39-4-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Minutes, 1997 - 1998; F-39-4-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Minutes, 1998 - 1999; F-39-4-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Minutes, reports, 1999; F-39-4-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 39-18)
    - Executive binder (Betty Dwyer), 1992 - 1994; F-39-4-3-0-22 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
    - Executive binder (Judy Einstein), vol. 1, 1992 - 1994; F-39-4-3-0-23 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
    - Executive binder (Judy Einstein), vol. 2, 1992 - 1994; F-39-4-3-0-24 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
    - Executive binder (Judy Einstein), vol. 3, 1992 - 1994; F-39-4-3-0-25 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
    - Executive binder (Maria Issa), vol. 1, 1994 - 1995; F-39-4-3-0-26 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
    - Executive binder (Maria Issa), vol. 2, 1994 - 1995; F-39-4-3-0-27 (Archival box - standard 39-19)
- Projects, programs and events files, 1981 - 2004; F-39-5; Analog originals: 1.74 m of textual records 13 photographs 19 sound recordings (25 audio cassettes) 1 multiple media record (1 optical disk - CD)
  Series comprises records relating to the activities undertaken by the Society to realize its educational, outreach and professional networking goals. Activities documented include the organization of networking events, conferences and panel sessions; development of professional and educational resources; and design of on-going outreach programs for educators, parents, primary- and secondary-school students and the general public. Records include correspondence; reports; grant applications and supporting documentation; handbooks and manuals; workshop and presentation material; and brochures and other publicity material. Series also includes photographs, audio cassettes and video cassettes.
  Note that in the arrangement of this series, a sub-series was created for each program or project that was either on-going or that generated a large quantity of records.
  - Events and projects files, 1981 - 2004; F-39-5-1; 46 cm of textual records 1 sound recording; Physical description: series includes 1 audio cassette.